Okay בוקר טוב, Boker Tov, today's דף daf is דף פ, Daf
Pei, 80, and we pick up at the bottom of, or
not so at the bottom, middle of עין ט עמוד ב Ayin
Tes Amud Beis where we're a little behind so let's try to
focus today. And we pick up with the משנה. mishna. We finally
after all of this discussion about walls and ditches and so on,
finally get around to the discussion about actually making the עירוב eruv
or the שיתוף shituf itself. So let's take a look. כיצד משתתפין
במבוי, Keitzad mishtatfin bamavoi, how do you do a שיתוף shituf of
the מבוי? mavoi? Just how do you gather the food? The middle
of עין ט עמוד ב, Ayin Tes Amud Beis, the משנה. mishna.
מניח את החבית, Maniach es hachavis,
you take the barrel, barrel of wine, or maybe dates or figs
or something because שיתוף shituf does not have to be bread. ואומר
הרי זו לכל בני המבוי, V'omer arei zu lechol bnei hamavoi, this
whole this is for all of the people of the מבוי. mavoi.
You are going everybody has to contribute food, but we're going to
find out a shortcut is if you're a צדיק, tzadik, you can
take some of your own food and transfer ownership to everybody and
then everybody's food, everybody now has a portion of the food in
this barrel.
But we didn't say this by the other עירוב. eruv. Well we're
going to.
We didn't discuss it at all by anything how you actually do
it. ומזכה להן, Umizakeh lahen,
now the point is you cannot transfer ownership without a second party.
You can't just say even though I can transfer something, give you
a gift without your consent because זכין לאדם שלא בפניו, zachin leadam
shelo befanav,
I can do a merit something for your benefit without your presence,
but I can't do it against your wishes. But if I wanted
to transfer you, give you my car, okay unless it was a
piece of junk that it was more trouble than it was worth,
if I wanted to give you my car, I could do it
without your consent, but I need a somebody else to for the
act of transfer. So I can go ahead and I can take
Charlie here and I can say Charlie, take possession of my car
for Rifka. Rifka has no idea what the heck I'm doing, but
it's a benefit for her, so I can do it without her
presence, but I need somebody else in the act. I can't transfer
it from one hand to the other. I haven't done some act
of transfer. So I need a second party. Okay, so how do
I get a second party here for this act? I got this
barrel full of, this barrel full of what do you call it,
of wine or dates or whatnot. How do I transfer it to
everybody in the מבוי? mavoi? So what do I do? ומזכה להן
על ידי בנו ובתו הגדולים, Umizakeh lahen al yedei bno u'vito hagedolim,
and you get somebody else. Now the most convenient people around are
the convenient people in my household. So
I can get one of my adult sons or daughters and say
here, take possession of this barrel and take possession of it for
everybody in the מבוי. mavoi. Which is why by the way that
you've never been asked by the Rabbi of to contribute some money
or some מצה matzah or some bread for the for our current
עירוב, eruv, because he takes it and he gives it to you
know somebody else. Says here, take possession of it for everybody in
the city. ועל ידי עבדו ושפחתו העברים, V'al yedei avdo v'shifchaso haivrim,
or Jewish male and female
servants/slaves. Because since they're Jewish that means that they are an independent
רשות, rishus, they're their own person. You might have a lien on
them for their labor but they're their own person, so their ownership
is their own. They're considered a separate יד yad like a separate
domain, a separate property. ועל ידי אשתו, V'al yedei ishto, or through
his wife. אבל אין מזכה לא על ידי בנו ובתו הקטנים, Aval
ein m'zakeh lo al yedei bno u'vito haktanim, but what you can't
do is transfer to your minor children. They're not considered a separate,
you know, sort of domain than you. Domain is not the right
word here but whatever, a separate ownership.
They're considered an extension of you. ולא על ידי עבדו ושפחתו הכנענים,
V'lo al yedei avdo v'shifchaso hakenanim, or your non-Jewish male and female
slave. They're considered your property. בפני שידן כידו Bifnei sheyadan kiyado and
as the משנה mishna says, their hand is like your hand. Putting
it into their hand they are not a independent ownership and therefore
it's still like taking it from my right hand to my left
hand. Michael raises the question does it literally mean adult or not?
תוספות Tosafos gets into that based on another גמרא Gemara based on
discussions we had before. If you're adult but if you are supported
by your father and you eat at the table or does he
provide you with food, to what degree do you establish, you know,
independence from your parents? Interesting question psychologists ask as well and we
all deal with when we have kids growing up. They could be
5,000 miles away in ישראל, Israel, but it's, you know, dear Dad,
please send money or something or dear Mom, please. So anyway, to
what degree are they really considered independent or not? That another גמרא
Gemara discusses. This גמרא Gemara does not. This גמרא Gemara is willing
to take this משנה mishna on face value that it's the mere
question about being adult even if they're living at your house. But
another גמרא Gemara does suggest that what's more critical to the question
of age might be the issue of actual dependence and financial dependence.
And it raises the possibility that even a minor who is financially
independent, it could happen, thank you, might be considered separate. A separate
domain. And תוספות Tosfos says what, what, what do you mean, since
when can a minor take possession of something? And that תוספות Tosfos
says well look, maybe it's different here and I just raise it
now because it's going to come up in the גמרא Gemara as
well
that since this is all a, it's a quasi-aspect of קנין, Kinyan,
but it's really also quasi-ritual, meaning it's not really like I'm trying
to transfer ownership of my car, right, where I, you know, it's
really more to have everybody participate in the ritual, so maybe the
standards are a little lower and therefore maybe a minor who is,
acts is independent, maybe for this הלכה, halacha, if not for other
הלכה, halacha, might be able to take possession, especially because what you
have is something הלכה halacha calls דעת אחר מקנה אותו. Da'as acher
makneh oso. It's not like somebody finds a lost object on the
street and they're the whole agent in taking possession of it where
that might require an adult. Here the person receiving can be more
passive because I am the active party and I am doing the
act of transference. And the other, that's דעת אחרת, Da'as acheres, a
separate will that is transferring and therefore it might more be effective,
be able to be effective with a minor maybe because it requires,
you know, more a person could be more passive and be in
the receiving. So that's the issue that maybe adult and child doesn't
mean literal, maybe it means dependent or independent in a practical way,
but the simple sense of the משנה Mishna is it's an issue
of adult versus child. I should also mention this comes up frequently
on ערב שבת, Erev Shabbos, a similar issue, because there's a הלכה
halacha that you're not allowed to give a gift on שבת, Shabbos,
you're not allowed to transfer קנין. Kinyan. You can't take any possession
on שבת. Shabbos. So what happens if you're going to somebody's house
and you want to bring over a bottle of wine or some
flowers or whatever you want to bring over? So the עיקר הלכה
ikar halacha is, is that if it's לצורך שבת letzorech Shabbos it's
allowed. But sometimes, you know, I don't know, you want to bring
over who knows, a book, which they might not read on שבת,
Shabbos, or you want to bring over wine but they might not
open it that שבת, Shabbos, they might have already have an open
bottle or whatever. So what often is done is you take your,
you call over your spouse or your בר מצוה Bar Mitzvah or
בת מצוה Bat Mitzvah kid and you say, here, take possession of
this for ערב שבת, Erev Shabbos, you do this, for our guests
that we're going to, you know, for the people we're going to
tomorrow and therefore when you give it to them it's already theirs.
Okay, if you forgot to do that what you could say is
you could bring over the gift and say, here, I wanted to
bring this but I'm not transferring ownership of it to you until
after שבת. Shabbos.
Unless it's all gone.
Unless it's all gone, but then we'll be drinking my wine, not
your wine. Yes, Rivka? No, then if it's if we're going to
drink it, then we can actually do it on שבת Shabbos because
it's לצורך שבת. letzorech Shabbos.
Can any of the other people, a woman, the wife, or the
slaves, can they be the the main actors in the עירוב?
Eruv? We're going to get to that in the גמרא. Gemara. Like
can they basically, can I go to, can I go to somebody's
house, knock on the door and the wife says, yeah, my husband
isn't home but don't worry, here's some bread. No, that's not what
you're saying.
Can the woman be the one to knock on the door and?
Yeah, definitely. Definitely. We'll see in the גמרא. Gemara. Definitely she can.
The question the גמרא Gemara has is the גמרא Gemara assumes the
standard financial arrangement in the time of, you know, which is in
the time of the גמרא, Gemara, which is the property was owned
by the husband and the wife was supported, and the question was
does the wife have the right to contribute of the husband's property
without his consent? But in the question of can the wife be
the actual person to be the active party, yes, absolutely. And we'll
see some of that in the גמרא. Gemara.
And and if a wife is is dependent on the husband, then
how can you do it? Are are they איש אחד ish echad
then according to the the view that you need an independent?
Right, so, so the, so the גמרא Gemara discusses that and it
discusses like the wife maybe has her own house and that establishes
her independence.
And everybody also has his own?
Yeah. So anyway, like I said, this משנה Mishna does is not
and the גמרא, Gemara, our גמרא Gemara is not bothered with the
practical question of dependency. It assumes adult versus child. And the only
the only people that are considered not independent, not הלכתית halachically independent,
are either children, under age, or non-Jewish slaves that are considered property.
Okay? It's another גמרא Gemara that says it's not just an issue
of adult versus child, it's an issue of practical dependency. So that
other גמרא Gemara works it through and speaks about and creates circumstances
in which the wife is independent.
We had that as well with the five five wives. Right. We
did have it and I remember I asked you can each wife
do her own.
And the answer is? No. No, I don't remember that. Oh, it
depends. It depends in circumstances where where the wives are תוספות Tosfos
there's a long תוספות Tosfos that discusses that. In circumstances where the
husband actually sends food to all of his wives,
assuming dependency is what's relevant then they would not be able to,
then they wouldn't do it on their own. But in cases, A,
the simple sense of this משנה Mishna doesn't buy into that, and
B, if he didn't send food to them תוספות Tosfos says if
he pays their food bill but doesn't actively send food to them
that that makes them more independent. So it's based on the circumstances.
Our משנה, Mishna, I want to reiterate, does not talk about the
question of who's feeding whom and assumes that if you're an adult
and you're a free person you're independent. Okay, let's take a look
at the גמרא. Gemara. אמר רבא. Amar Rava. רב יהודה Rav Yehuda
*Rav Yehuda* said רב יהודה Rav Yehuda *Rav Yehuda*, חבית ששיתופי מבואות
mevo'os צריך להגביה מן הקרקע טפח tefach, *chavis sheshitufey mevo'os tzarich lehagbi'ah
min hakarka tefach*. When you transfer ownership, I give this barrel of
wine over to Charlie here, he's taking possession for all of you
guys, he has to lift it off of the ground a טפח
tefach. *tefach* because that's a קניין של הגבהה *kinyan of hagba'ah* of
lifting, and it has to be a טפח tefach, *tefach*. Now the
question is can we infer from here that standard הגבהה *hagba'ah* is
one טפח tefach *tefach*? Because there's actually a lot of contradictory evidence
in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* and sometimes it seems like it's three
טפחים *tefachim*. So תוספות Tosafot *Tosafos* says you cannot infer from here
because remember three טפחים *tefachim* is no longer לבוד *lavud*, so that's
a significant amount. תוספות Tosafot *Tosafos* says you can't make a general
statement from here, again, this is partly a קניין *kinyan* but it's
partly a ritual, so the standards might be lower here. So just
because here a טפח *tefach* suffices doesn't mean always a טפח *tefach*
suffices. What?
הגבהה *Hagba'ah*? Yeah, there's a question, things that you can do הגבהה
*hagba'ah*, can you do משיכה *mshicha* with, but anyway. Okay. אמר רבא
*Amar Rava*, הני תרתי מילי סבי דפומבדיתא sabei de'Pumbedita אמרינהו *hani
tartei mili sabei dePumbedisa amrin'hu*. The following two things the elders of
פומבדיתא Pumbedita, *Pumbedisa*, which were שמואל'ס Shmuel's *Shmuel's* ישיבה *yeshiva*, and the
elders of פומבדיתא *Pumbedisa* refer to רב Rav יהודה *Rav Yehuda* who
was the main student of a main student of שמואל Shmuel, *Shmuel*.
So the elders of פומבדיתא *Pumbedisa* said: חדא הא *chada ha*, one
what we just said which is אמר רב Rav's יהודה *Amar Rav
Yehuda*, you have to pick it a טפח *tefach* off the ground,
A it has to be a טפח *tefach* but B a טפח
*tefach* suffices. ואידך *Ve'idach*, and the other one is המקדש אם טעם
מלא לוגמיו יצא ואם לאו לא יצא *ham'kadesh im ta'am melo lugmav
yatza ve'im
lav lo yatza*. Person makes קידוש *Kiddush*, you can't just make קידוש
*Kiddush* and take a tiny little sip, you have to drink the
amount that fills up one of your cheeks, and what? הבדלה *Havdala*
also? Presumably, yes. And if not, you're לא יצא *lo yatza*. So
תוספות Tosafot *Tosafos* has a whole interesting discussion because we also know
that the כוס *kos* of קידוש *Kiddush* has to be a רביעית
*revi'is* and there's another גמרא Gemara *Gemara* that makes it sound like
מלא לוגמיו *malo lugmav* is more than a רביעית *revi'is*, which is
a little bit of a problem because how can you drink
a מלא לוגמיו *malo lugmav*? Right. Anyway, basically it says it must
be מלא לוגמיו *malo lugmav* is less than a רביעית *revi'is*, but
anyway there's a minimum amount of the כוס *kos* של קידוש *shel
Kiddush* that you have to drink. Okay, we're not going to get
into details about that, but we do פסחים *Pesachim* we'll talk about
that more. Okay. אמר רב Rav, חביבא *Amar Rav Chaviva*, הני נמי
סבי דפומבדיתא אמרינהו *hani nami sabei dePumbedisa amrin'hu*. The following thing was
also said by the elders of פומבדיתא *Pumbedisa*, רב Rav יהודה *Rav
Yehuda*, but since we're using this phrase סבי דפומבדיתא *sabei dePumbedisa* we
collect a couple of related statements. דאמר רב Rav? יהודה אמר שמואל
Shmuel. *De'amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel*, עושים מדורה לחיה בשבת *osim medura
l'chaya b'Shabbos*. רב Rav: יהודה *Rav Yehuda* again in the name of
שמואל Shmuel *Shmuel*, עושים מדורה לחיה בשבת *osim medura l'chaya b'Shabbos*. You
can make a bonfire for a woman who has just given birth
on שבת shabbos *Shabbos*. She's a חולה *chola* and therefore she's considered
יש בה סכנה *yesh bah sakana* and this is considered to be
for necessary for her health. So סברו מינה *savru minah*, we thought
to say about that, לחיה אין לחולה לא *l'chaya in l'chola lo*.
For a woman who's given birth, yes; for a normal sick person,
presumably even a חולה שיש בו סכנה *chola she-yesh bo sakana*, we
don't assume necessarily that a normal חולה *chola*, even one that's יש
בו סכנה *yesh bo sakana* has the need of heat, meaning of
this type degree of heat, maybe if it's a particular case where
it's clear they do, yes, but we wouldn't necessarily assume this. בימות
הגשמים אין בימות החמה לא *B'yemot hageshamim in b'yemot hachama lo*. In
the winter, yes; in the summer, no. איתמר Itmar, *Itmar*, but it
was taught, אמר רב Rav's חייא בר אבין אמר שמואל Shmuel. *Amar
Rav Chiya bar Avin amar Shmuel*. No, that שמואל Shmuel *Shmuel* qualified
it and he said הקיז דם ונצטנן *hikiz dam venitztanen*. If somebody
let blood and they're feeling chilly, עושים לו מדורה בשבת ואפילו בתקופת
תמוז *osim lo medura b'Shabbos va'afilu b'tekufas Tammuz*. You could make a
bonfire on שבת shabbos *Shabbos* even if it's the middle of the
summer. So basically anytime a sick person who is potentially יש בו
סכנה *yesh bo sakana* feels chilly, you can go ahead and make
a fire. That is considered definitely a concern of צרכי החולה *tzorchei
hachola* even if it's already hot outside and we do not hesitate
about that. אמר אמימר *Amar Ameimar*, הני נמי סבי דפומבדיתא אמרינהו *hani
nami sabei dePumbedisa amrin'hu*. The following thing was also said by the
elders of פומבדיתא *Pumbedisa*. איתמר Itmar, *Itmar*, איזו היא אשרה סתם *eizu
hi ashera stam*. What, when we speak about an אשרה *ashera*, an
אשרה *ashera* is a tree that is worshipped for what's it called
in English? There's a word, אשרות *Asheros* I know they name them.
Anyway, I think they say it's for Ishtar, which is the female
goddess. Babylonian.
Babylonian goddess. So anyway, it's in the תורה *Torah* a lot. אשרותיהן
תשרפון באש *ashiroteihen tisrefun ba'esh*, burning their אשרה *ashera* trees. So what
type of a tree can we assume is an אשרה *ashera* by
based on their practices without knowing black and white that it was
worshipped? So אמר רב Rav *Amar Rav*, so רב Rav *Rav* says
כל שמשמשי עבודה זרה avoda zara, שומרים אותה *kol she-mishamshei avoda zara
shomrim osah*. Anything that is protected by, guarded by the attendants of
the idol, like the priests maybe, ואין טועמין מפירותיה *ve'ein to'amin mipiroseha*.
And they refuse to actually partake of the fruit. So that's a
strong indicator that this is an אשרה *ashera*. ושמואל אמר *U'Shmuel amar*,
and שמואל Shmuel's *Shmuel* says כגון דאמרי הני תמרי לשיכרא דבי נצרפי
*kegon de'amri hanei tamrei l'shichra de-Bei Netzarphei*. That if they say we're
going to use the dates of this tree to make the beer
for דבי נצרפי *de-Bei Netzarphei*, which is apparently the name of an
עבודה זרה *avoda zara*.
Steinsaltz speculates that נצרפי *Netzarphei* is from another word which means fire
and it was referring to because the
Zoroastrian they had a whole special fire ritual so it... is like
נסרפי I think נסרף. nisraf. Anyway, we're going to use this, these,
to make beer for this,
for this church, for this temple. דשתו ליה ביום חגא Dashtu lei
be'yom chaga and the beer will be drunk on their on the
special on this special religious holiday. Now yes, good question. So it
seems like according to שמואל, Shmuel's, that they use it for maybe
it's dedicated for it's not just they happen to get fruit from
it. It's dedicated to provide for it a material for religious rituals,
but it doesn't mean it's an object of worship. And clearly an
אשירה Asherah is for that specific... no this specific tree in this
city they you know they watch this tree and they do a
whole ritual and they collect the fruit and they use it for
this practice. So, but fine, it doesn't mean they worship the tree.
So some ראשונים Rishonim say yeah for him it would be like
a rabbinic extension of an אשירה, Asherah, it wouldn't really be an
אשירה Asherah because a real אשירה Asherah is something that is worshipped.
Okay. ואמרו לי סבי דפומבדיתא Va'amru lei sabei de'Pumbedita okay with what
was
said before.
No he's saying even that
case שמואל. Shmuel, Okay and said to me the elders of פומבדיתא,
again it's רב Rav יהודה was a student of שמואל Shmuel so
he's a little biased here, but anyway,
הלכתא כוותיה דשמואל, Hilcheta ke'vatei de'Shmuel,
we rule like שמואל. Shmuel, Okay now back to our business. מיתיבי,
Meitivei, there's an interesting little digression. כיצד משתתפין במבוי? Keitzad mishtatfin be'mavoi?
How do you do a שיתוף shituf for מבוי? mavoi? מביאים חבית
של יין ושל שמן ושל תמרים, Mevi'in chavit shel yayin ve'shel shemen
ve'shel temarim, you bring a barrel, it could be oil wine or
oil or dates, ושל גרוגרות ושל פגין ve'shel grogerot ve'shel pagin or
figs ושל שאר מיני פירות ve'shel she'ar minei peirot other types of
fruit. אם משלו, Im mishelo, right notice it's not an עירוב חצירות,
eruv chatzeirot, it's a שיתוף, shituf, so it doesn't have to be
bread, it can be anything. אם משלו, Im mishelo, if
I'm using mine, צריך
לזכות, tzarich lezakot, I have to transfer ownership of it to the
rest of the people of the מבוי. mavoi. This is a שיתוף
מבואות. shituf mevo'ot.
I know, because it's a שיתוף shituf it doesn't have to be
bread. An עירוב eruv would have to be bread. Okay, אם משלו,
im mishelo, if I'm using mine, צריך לזכות, tzarich lezakot, I have
to transfer ownership
of it. ואם משלהן, ve'im mishelahen,
if they actually were the ones that contributed, צריך להודיע, tzarich lehodia,
I have to let them know, meaning
maybe I don't know somehow they happen to be storing some wine
in my basement so I have access to their food but I
have to let them know hey guys I'm using your wine to
make this שיתוף shituf because... Before or after? No, I have to
tell them beforehand, okay that's the whole point, because just I can't
just I can't take if they're not agreeable to the use of
their food it doesn't work so if it happens to be their
food I still have to make sure that they are informed and
agreeable to this.
צריך להודיע, tzarich lehodia, where am I? ומגביהה מן הקרקע משהו. U'magbihah
min ha'karka mashehu. So and you lift it up a little bit
from the ground presumably in the case of לזכות lezakot where I'm
transferring ownership, okay? So you see that it's a little bit it
doesn't have to be a טפח, remember that's how we started this
whole סבי דפומבדיתא because we were talking about a טפח.
So the גמרא Gemara's says no מהו משהו נמי דקאמר טפח. Mahu
mashehu nami de'ka'amar tefach. Yeah a little bit means a טפח, that's
enough. I should say that it sounds like you should be lifting
it up even if you're already starting with theirs, which makes it
sound like again it's not just about transferring ownership it's also about
doing some type of a ritual. You know it's like you lift
it up and say this is for the this is for the
שיתוף. shituf. Okay, but again that's what's sort of being played out
here is a how much is it about real transferring of ownership
and how much is it about sort of making this somewhat you
know doing some appropriate ritual. Okay, but if it's starts off as
your property you have to at least transfer it to another person
and that person has to lift it a טפח off the ground.
Of course setting this whole שיתוף shituf before finishing up what he's
doing in עירוב? eruv?
What do you mean? We've been moving between עירוב eruv and שיתוף
shituf for a while. Yeah I know,
how come this wasn't the first משנה Mishnah of the מסכת? masechet?
All right I don't know. Okay, so
okay. Now the גמרא Gemara says like this. איתמר, was taught, שיתופי
מבואות. shitufai mevo'ot. Back to square one, making a שיתוף. shituf. רב
אמר אין צריך לזכות, Rav amar ein tzarich lezakot, against the משנה
mishnah that said explicitly צריך לזכות, tzarich lezakot, you have to transfer
ownership. רב Rav says no, you can make it as some ritual
and you don't have to transfer ownership. If you take your own
property your own wine and you just say this is for the
שיתוף shituf and you don't have to transfer ownership. Now תוספות Tosafot
points out that and רש"י Rashi actually points out that the logic
behind it the גמרא's Gemara going to just ask what the authority
is to say that since the משנה mishnah says you do. But
the logic behind it is you could have just said look the
whole thing is got purely ritualized and you don't really have to
own it altogether. רש"י Rashi does not go that far. He said
that what's going to be the what's going to be the effect
if
if we don't do this שיתוף? shituf? Nobody's going to be able
to use this street or the חצר. chatzer. So you all I
if I'm the one here doing it maybe I don't know maybe
you don't even care but I care, okay? I really want to
be able to use that street, I'm the one that's taking care
of this stuff. So from if I'm going to try to transfer
this to you every now and then we say that if there
is sufficient גמירת דעת, gemirat da'at, there is I am sufficiently you
know I'm strongly committed and motivated and I really want something to
happen, my sort
of
intention... and you guys are getting in my way because you're not
around to help me make the עירוב eruv whatever, my will to
transfer this bit here, this barrel of wine, will do it even
without another party. It'll just my דעת daas alone can do it.
That's how they explain רב's Rav idea that you don't need an
act of transference because you're actually getting in my way, you're creating
a problem, I'm trying to fix a problem, so my will can
do it alone. Again,
you could have said that maybe it's more that he just considered
it more of a ritual than an actual transference, but that's the
way רש״י Rashi explains it. Again, so it's against our משנה, mishna,
but אין צריך לזכות, ein tzarich lizkos, you don't actually have to
transfer the property. ושמואל אמר צריך לזכות. u'Shmuel amar tzarich lizkos.
No, you have to like the משנה. mishna. Now how about a
case not being discussed here? עירוב תחומין. eruv techumin. How about putting
a תחום techum for somebody else? I'm going to put down bread
there so Michael can walk two thousand אמות amos more, you know,
east of the city. רב אמר צריך לזכות. Rav amar tzarich lizkos.
Ah, that case everybody's like the mirror image here. If I want
that to work for Michael, then I have to transfer that bread
to Michael, you know, has to be Michael's bread or I have
to have somebody take possession of it for Michael. ושמואל אמר אין
צריך לזכות. u'Shmuel amar ein tzarich lizkos.
In that case שמואל Shmuel. says you don't have to. Okay? So
they're flipped about what they would normally say. So why רב, Rav
the logic of רב Rav is again there, you know, I'm doing
Michael a favor, it's not like without doing this I'm not going
to be able to use the courtyard or the street, so I
don't have the same degree of גמר דעת, gemar daas, I don't
have the same, you know, sort of strong motivation to make it
happen, so there Michael really has to own the bread and I
need him to either be his bread or I have to transfer
possession. That's עירוב תחומין. eruv techumin. עירוב חצירות, eruv chatzeiros, שמואל's Shmuel,
logic would be that again that that is
let me just check שמואל's, Shmuel תוספות Tosafot gives a few explanations
for שמואל, Shmuel hold on.
Yeah, so תוספות Tosafot says maybe because you know you do עירוב
תחומין eruv techumin for דבר מצוה, dvar mitzvah, we normally assume you're
doing עירוב תחומין eruv techumin for דבר מצוה, dvar mitzvah, so that
makes it more able to be effective without a מעשה קנין, maaseh
kinyan, or because עירוב תחומין eruv techumin is less about sort of
creating some joint ownership like the courtyard is, maybe again it requires
less actual transference of property the same way עירוב חצירות eruv chatzeiros
does. So you could sort of give arguments in both directions, but
שמואל Shmuel says like the משנה, mishna, you need to do it
for עירוב חצירות, eruv chatzeiros, and we don't have a משנה mishna
like this for שיתופי מבואות, shitufay mevo'os, right? And we don't have
an עירוב eruv like this by עירוב תחומין. eruv techumin. So he
says by עירוב תחומין eruv techumin you don't have to, you can
do, I can put this bread down for Michael without it being
Michael's bread. ורב אמר ve'Rav amar the opposite: you don't need it
for שיתופי מבואות, shitufay mevo'os, you do need it for עירוב תחומין.
eruv techumin. Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara, says like this: בשלמא
לשמואל הכא תנן והכא לא תנן. bishlama le'Shmuel hacha tenan vehacha lo
tenan.
I get for שמואל, Shmuel it's very consistent with the משנה. mishna.
By שיתופי מבואות shitufay mevo'os it speaks about transferring ownership, by עירוב
תחומין eruv techumin it doesn't. So by עירוב תחומין eruv techumin I
can do it for somebody else without an actual act of transferring
ownership. אלא לרב מאי טעמא? ela le'Rav mai ta'ama? How about רב?
Even if you, I can understand why you would demand it by
עירוב תחומין, eruv techumin, how can you go against the משנה? mishna?
The משנה mishna says that by שיתוף shituf you do need it,
how could you say you don't need it? So the גמרא Gemara
says: תנאי היא, tannai hi, it's a debate of תנאים. tannaim. דאמר
רב יהודה אמר רב, de'amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav, because רב יהודה
said in the name of רב: מעשה בכלתה של רבי אושעיא, maaseh
be'kallasa shel Rabbi Oshaya, there's a story of the daughter-in-law of רבי
אושעיא Rabbi Oshaya שהלכה לבית המרחץ, she'halcha l'veis hamerchatz,
she went to the bathhouse ערב שבת erev Shabbos וחשכה לה, v'chashka
la,
and it got dark and she wasn't around to make, participate in
the
עירוב, eruv, וערבה לה חמותה, v'airva la chamossa, and her mother-in-law took
care of it for her. Now which עירוב eruv are we talking
about? רש״י Rashi says we're talking about עירוב תחומין eruv techumin and
she was caught outside of the city.
But תוספות Tosafot says: no, no, no, the whole problem with רב's
statement is that he's against the משנה. mishna. The משנה mishna explicitly
says you need to be מזכה, mezakeh, you need to transfer it
by עירוב חצירות, eruv chatzeiros, so רב needs to find a תנא
tanna that says you don't need to do that. שיתוף מבואות, shituf
mevo'os, yeah, we're sort of putting them together, but right, שיתוף מבואות.
shituf mevo'os. So we so therefore תוספות Tosafot says: no, no, no,
we're talking about she just happened to not be home ערב שבת
erev Shabbos and therefore we had a problem because we needed her
to participate in the שיתוף מבואות shituf mevo'os and she wasn't around.
So her mother-in-law took care of it for her. So she did
a שיתוף מבואות shituf mevo'os without her without her participation. Okay? Presence.
So ואתא לקמיה דרבי חייא, v'asa l'kamay de'Rabbi Chiya,
and it came to רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya ואסר, ve'assar, and he
said it's forbidden. אמר לו רבי ישמעאל ברבי יוסי: amar lo Rabbi
Yishmael beRabbi Yossi: בבלאי, Bavlai, Babylonian, כל כך אתה מחמיר בעירובין? kol
kach ata machmir b'eiruvin? You're so strict in עירובין eiruvin that you
don't let some you know her mother-in-law do it for her? כך
אמר אבא, kach amar Abba, this is what my father רבי יוסי
Rabbi Yossi said: כל שאתה יכול להקל בעירוב הקל, kol she'ata yachol
lehakel b'eiruv hakel, as much as you can be lenient by עירוב
eruv you should be lenient, which is a theme that we've definitely
seen before, right? הלכה כדברי המיקל בעירוב. halacha k'divrei hameikel b'eiruv. So
what was at stake here that her mother-in-law did it? What was
being debated? איבעיא להו. Ibaia lehu. And the question was raised: משל
חמותה עירבה לה, mishel chamota iervah lah, did her mother-in-law was the
one who contributed the food, ומשום דלא זכתה לה, umishum delo zachatah
lah, and the problem was, was that she you did not transfer
ownership, which was the issue that we spoke before, about whether you
have to transfer ownership or not, the debate of רב and שמואל.
Shmuel And then this, if that was true, this would be a
proof that רבי ישמעאל ברבי יוסי Rabbi Yishmael b'Rabbi Yossi says, you
can be lenient, you don't have to actually transfer ownership through an
act of transferring ownership. And that would defend רב's position that way.
או דילמא, Od dilma, or do we say, משלה עירבה, mishelah iervah,
no actually she went to the, you know, cupboard of her daughter-in-law
and she gave some of her daughter-in-law's food. So what was the
issue? ומשום דשלא מדעתה, umishum deshalo m'da'atah, and it was because the
other point we said, that if you have access to the other
person's food, you still have to make them aware. So what was
the issue? Was the issue that the person wasn't aware but it
was her food, or was it that it was even her food
and that you and you don't have to do an act of
transferring the food? אמר להן ההוא מדרבנן, Amar lehen hahu meirabbanan, one
of the rabbinic students said, רבי יעקב שמיה, Rabbi Yaakov shmeh, לדידי
מפרשא לי מיניה דרבי יוחנן, ledidi mifarsha lei minei d'Rabbi Yochanan, I
heard this explained to me in the name of רבי יוחנן: Rabbi
Yochanan: משל חמותה עירבה, mishel chamota iervah, he had a tradition that
this was her mother-in-law's food, ומשום דלא זכתה לה, umishum delo zachatah
lah, and the problem was that she didn't transfer ownership to the
daughter-in-law. אמר ליה רבי זירא לרבי יעקב, Amar lei Rabbi Zeira leRabbi
Yaakov, so רבי זירא Rabbi Zeira said to רבי יעקב, Rabbi Yaakov,
this was the rabbi was the name of the rabbi who's רבי
יעקב, Rabbi Yaakov, בריה דבת יעקב. breh d'bat Yaakov. I don't know
why they take out the word בריה, breh, but anyway, the daughter
of the son of the daughter of יעקב. Yaakov. So what happened
to his father's name? So if you look at רש"י, Rashi, רש"י
Rashi said, אביו לא היה הגון לפיכך לא הזכירו. Aviv lo hayah
hagun, lefichach lo hizkiro. They had some issue with the father, so
they wouldn't want to mention it. So they said the daughter, anyway,
so he was named after his mother. Anyway, כי מטית התם, ki
matis hatam, when you get there to ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, עקיף
וזיל לסולמה דצור, akif v'zil l'sulama d'Tzur, take the roundabout way of
going of getting to where you're going and go by the sort
of the ladders of צור. Tzor. If you take a look, Steinsaltz
has a nice picture of it, but it basically means it's like,
you know, drive down the coast. Don't cut through from בבל Bavel
to ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael this way, go like up around and
go down by Tyre and go down the coast, because then you'll
give you access as to this person I want you to talk
to. Okay, so take the roundabout way and בעי מיניה מרבי יעקב
בר אידי. ba'ei minei miRabbi Yaakov bar Idi. And ask רבי יעקב
בר אידי Rabbi Yaakov bar Idi what he knows about this story,
about what was at stake. Was it the stake whether you have
the daughter-in-law's דעת, da'at, or was it a stake that was used
the mother-in-law's food? בעי מיניה, Ba'ei minei, so he asked him. So
he said: משל חמותה עירבה. mishel chamota iervah. It was the mother-in-law's
food. ומשום דלא זכתה לה. umishum delo zachatah lah. Oh, I'm sorry,
that was a question. Is it משל mishel and בעי מיניה, ba'ei
minei, ask him: משל חמותה עירבה ומשום דלא זכתה? mishel chamota iervah
umishum delo zachatah? Was it the mother-in-law's food and because the issue
was that she didn't transfer ownership? או דילמא משלה עירבה, Od dilma
mishelah iervah, it was her own food, ומשום דשלא מדעתה, umishum deshalo
m'da'atah, and it was done without her awareness? אמר ליה, Amar lei,
so he said back then, משל חמותה עירבה לה, mishel chamota iervah
lah, so this is what רבי יעקב בר אידי Rabbi Yaakov bar
Idi said back, it was the mother-in-law's food, ומשום דלא זכתה לה,
umishum delo zachatah lah, and because she didn't transfer ownership. So that
was a long discussion, was a fascinating little story, but what we
see is again that there's an opinion that you know רבי ישמעאל
ברבי יוסי Rabbi Yishmael b'Rabbi Yossi says don't worry you don't have
to be מזכה, mezakeh, be מיקל. meikel. Okay, so and again the
way תוספות Tosafot, understands this, this was a case about שיתוף מבואות
shituf mavo'ot or עירוב חצרות, eruv chatzerot, and you see, although the
משנה Mishnah says you have to transfer ownership by שיתוף מבואות, shituf
mavo'ot, in this story there was רבי ישמעאל ברבי יוסי Rabbi Yishmael
b'Rabbi Yossi that said that you did not. Okay, by the way,
תוספות Tosafot lists a whole list of cases like which are we
in general more lenient for or more strict for? עירוב תחומין eruv
techumin or עירוב חצרות? eruv chatzerot? And תוספות Tosafot says there's really
no real, like sometimes it's one sometimes the other, there's no real
consistency. First of all he says, if רש"י Rashi is right, although
it doesn't work as well in the גמרא, Gemara that what's being
debated here is whether you need to be מזכה mezakeh by עירוב
תחומין eruv techumin or not, what's being discussed is עירוב תחומין, eruv
techumin, he says it actually works out, because רבי ישמעאל ברבי יוסי
Rabbi Yishmael b'Rabbi Yossi that was lenient holds that תחומין techumin is
דרבנן, derabbanan, and the one that was strict, whichever that was, the
first opinion, held that תחומין techumin was דאורייתא. de'oraita. So actually that
might explain something of what was going on. But if you take
a quick look at the end of this תוספות, Tosafot רב אמר
אין צריך לזכות, Rav amar ein tzarich lizakos, תוספות Tosafot is about
six lines, about eight lines before it ends where it says the
line starts with צריך פת. tzarich pas. תוספות Tosafot says: ויש דברים
שאנו מחמירים בתחומין טפי מטפי, V'yesh devarim she'anu machmirin bitechumin tfei bitfei,
sometimes we're more strict by תחומין, techumin, דבתחומין בעי שתי סעודות לכל
אחד, d'bitechumin ba'ei shtei se'udot l'chol echad, by תחומין techumin everybody who
wants to be part of the עירוב תחומין eruv techumin has to
contribute two meals' worth. ובחצרות בזמן שהן מרובין סגי במזון שתי סעודות
לכולם ובזמן שהן מועטין סגי בגרוגרת לכל אחד. Uvechatzerot bizman shehein merubim
sagi bemazon shtei se'udot lekulam, uvizman shehein mu'atin sagi kegrogeret l'chol echad.
But by תחומין techumin you can have two meals' worth for everybody
combined, and we'll see that in a coming up משנה. Mishnah. So
that's one way we're more lenient by חצרות. chatzerot. כדאמרינן בפרקין והשולח
עירוב ביד חרש שוטה וקטן אינו עירוב לתחומין. Kid'amrinan b'pirkin v'hashole'ach eruv
beyad cheresh shoteh v'katan eino eruv latechumin. And but and and if
you for תחומין, techumin, if you want to send somebody who's not
a בר דעת bar da'at to put down your עירוב תחומין eruv
techumin it doesn't work. ובחצרות קטן גובה עירוב. Uvechatzerot katan goveih eruv.
By חצרות chatzerot if it's not your child, somebody else's child, okay,
can do the עירוב. eruv. So anyway, sometimes we're more strict by
עירוב תחומין. eruv techumin. and sometimes we're more and sometimes we're more
lenient and basically there's not always consistency about the way this works.
Why are you conflating the two? The שיטות shitos of מבואות and
the עירוב חצרות? eiruv chatzeiros? Why are you conflating the two? Is
the משנה Mishnah saying simply these are all שיטות? shitos? I don't
know, the גמרא Gemara just assumes it's not different. Okay, so let's
take a look. Okay, anyway, and here, so anyway, תוספות Tosafot says
those are cases where we're stricter by תחומין, techumim, but according to
שמואל, Shmuel. we're stricter by עירוב חצרות. eiruv chatzeiros. By עירוב חצרות
eiruv chatzeiros you actually have to do a transfer, whereas by תחומין
techumim you don't. Okay, so just anyway, I think I'm confusing you
all, but let's basically just step back. What we have is that
the משנה Mishnah says you have to actually transfer your property by
חצרות. chatzeiros. And שמואל Shmuel says you wouldn't have to do it
by תחומין. techumim. Okay? By תחומין, techumim, I can put it down
for you and it doesn't have to actually be your property. רב
says the reverse. You have to by חצרות, chatzeiros, you don't have
to do it against the משנה, Mishnah, but it works into this
whole story about the daughter-in-law. By חצרות chatzeiros you don't have to
do it, and by תחומין techumim you do have to do it.
Okay? So, and תוספות Tosafot just points out that it's not that
there's sometimes we're more strict by one, sometimes by the other, so
it's not like it's always one is the more strict category. And
here, there's debating which one do you need to do the transfer
for and which one do you not. And now let's see how
the גמרא Gemara concludes. Four lines down. אמר רב נחמן: Amar Rav
Nachman: נקטינן, Naktinan, we take as a position, אחד עירובי תחומין ואחד
עירובי חצרות ואחד שיתופי מבואות, echad eiruvei techumim v'echad eiruvei chatzeiros v'echad
shituyfei mevo'os, whether עירוב תחומין, eiruv techumim, whether עירוב חצרות—we eiruv chatzeiros
haven't mentioned עירוב חצרות eiruv chatzeiros yet, now we're mentioning it explicitly—and
whether שיתוף מבואות, shituf mevo'os, in all those cases צריך לזכות. tzarich
l'zakos. So as opposed to what we've been saying until now, which
is at least one of them you didn't have to—רב and שמואל
Shmuel debated which one you didn't have to, and we said try
to be as lenient as possible by עירובין—here Eiruvin the גמרא Gemara
actually concludes that you actually have to. Okay? And that is, and
that is how we hold. תוספות Tosafot says וכן הלכה. v'chein halacha.
And now the גמרא Gemara goes on, there's one final עירוב eiruv
we haven't spoken about yet, which we haven't talked about, עירוב תבשילין.
eiruv tavshilin. We haven't spoken about this entire מסכת, masechet, it really
gets discussed in ביצה. Beitzah. It's really not a similar discussion except
the word עירוב, eiruv, but the גמרא Gemara throws it in. So
the גמרא Gemara says like this. צריך לזכות. Tzarich l'zakos. בעי רב
נחמן: Ba'ei Rav Nachman: עירובי תבשילין, צריך לזכות eiruvei tavshilin tzarich l'zakos?
או אין צריך לזכות? tzarich l'zakos, The rabbi is doing an עירוב
תבשילין eiruv tavshilin and as a backup everybody does it in their
home, but as a backup he does it for everybody in the
city. Does he have to actually, for it to work for everybody
in the city, does he have to do an act of transferring
it to them or not? Or is it enough? Someone mentions the
language of the ברכה beracha is לכל בני העיר. l'chol b'nei ha'ir.
Right, right, right, it's true as well. When you're doing it yourself,
that's true, you use in the language that you're doing it for
everybody in the city. That is true. Okay, we'll discuss that more
when we see it in ביצה, Beitzah, that discussion about doing it
for other people. So do you have to be מזכה mezakeh or
not? So it says, אמר רב יוסף: amar Rav Yosef: ומה תיבעי
ליה? u'mah tiba'ei leh? I don't understand what question that is, whether,
if you want it to work for other people, do you have
to transfer ownership or not? לא שמיע ליה הא דאמר רב נחמן
בר אדא אמר שמואל: Lo shmei leh ha d'amar Rav Nachman bar
Adda amar Shmuel: עירובי תבשילין eiruvei tavshilin, צריך לזכות? Didn't he hear
the teaching in the name of שמואל Shmuel that you do have
to transfer the ownership if you want it to work for other
people? אמר ליה אביי: Amar leh Abaye: פשיטא דלא שמיע ליה. peshita
d'lo shmei leh. Of course he didn't hear that teaching. דאי שמיע
ליה מה תיבעי ליה? De'i shmei leh mah tiba'ei leh? If he
had heard it, what would his question have been? I don't understand
the question. Don't you know so-and-so? Of course I didn't know so-and-so,
that's why I was asking. Okay, so anyway, אמר ליה אטו עירובי
תחומין? amar leh atu eiruvei techumim? He says, no, no, no, maybe
he heard it and maybe he's going rogue.
Maybe he heard it and he doesn't care, and I'll show you
he doesn't always seem to pay attention to those things. עירובי תחומין
מי לא אמר שמואל אין צריך לזכות? Eiruvei techumim mi lo amar
Shmuel ein tzarich l'zakos? Look, שמואל Shmuel. says you don't have to
transfer ownership for עירוב תחומין. eiruv techumim. ואמר איהו, V'amar ihu, and
he, רב נחמן, Rav Nachman, just got through saying
a few lines ago, צריך לזכות, that by עירוב תחומין eiruv techumim
you do have to. So maybe he's not buying into שמואל'ס positions.
So maybe he knew that שמואל Shmuel said this here by עירוב
תבשילין eiruv tavshilin and he didn't care, maybe he was prepared to
be more lenient than שמואל. Shmuel So הכי השתא? hachi hashta? The
גמרא Gemara says, whoa, whoa, one minute. How do you compare them?
בשלמא התם פליגי רב ושמואל. Bishlama hatam pligi Rav u'Shmuel. First of
all, there, by whether you need it by עירוב תחומין eiruv techumim
or עירוב חצרות, eiruv chatzeiros, there were opinions articulated on both sides.
There was a debate of רב and שמואל Shmuel for both of
those issues. וקא משמע לן כחומרי דמר וכחומרי דמר. V'ka mashma lan
k'chumrei d'mar u'k'chumrei d'mar. And he teaches us, what we don't normally
say by עירובין, Eiruvin, normally we're as מקיל meikel as we can
be, but he teaches us here we'll adopt each person's more stringent
position. So he's not rejecting what other people say, he's just there's
different opinions and he's being מחמיר machmir here on both sides. אבל
הכא, Aval hacha, but here, by עירוב תבשילין, eiruv tavshilin, אי איתא
דשמיע ליה, ei isa d'shmei leh, had he heard that שמואל Shmuel
said you need to do it by עירוב תבשילין, eiruv tavshilin, and
nobody says otherwise, so מי איכא דמאן דפליג? mi ika d'man d'palig?
Nobody else said anything else. So had he known שמואל said it,
without knowing that there's another opinion, of course he would have gone
like שמואל. And it ends there, which basically makes it sound like
שמואל says it, nobody debates it, so of course you need it
by עירוב תבשילין eiruv tavshilin as well. keep it in mind for
you know I don't know six months from now whatever it is
when we get to ביצה *Beitzah* a year from now and that's
when we'll have the more direct discussion okay but but this גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* at least concludes that if you wanted to work for
other people you have to transfer ownership. Okay. So now the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* continues. ההוא תורזינא *hahu turzina* there is a certain like
a weapons officer apparently that he you know in his he oversaw
the armory of the city and he was living in the city
דרבי זירא *d'Rebbi Zeira* in I'm sorry דהוה בשבבותיה דרבי זירא *de-havu
beshivutei d'Rebbi Zeira* lived in the neighborhood of רבי זירא *Rebbi Zeira*.
אמרו ליה *amru lei* they said to him he was a non-Jew
אוגר לן רשותך *ogir lan reshushach* rent us your property sure my
property where I've got all the weapons so לא אוגר להו *lo
ogir lehu* so he refused so אתו לקמיה דרבי זירא *atu lekamei
d'Rebbi Zeira* they came to רבי זירא *Rebbi Zeira* right what are
we going to do we need to make an עירוב eruv. *eiruv*
and the non-Jew won't rent us the property so אמרו ליה *amru
lei* he said to them אמרו ליה *amru lei* they said to
him מהו למיגר מדביתהו *mahu le-meigar mideveithayu* how about going to his
wife and asking his wife if she could contribute right so you
know again this whole thing about like a ritual rather than a
real thing because if it was a real thing you know his
wife doesn't have the right to rent out this guy's property but
if it's a ritual maybe we'll just talk to his wife even
though he said that he refuses אמרו להו *amru lehu* like mom
when dad says no exactly exactly אמרו להו *amru lehu* he said
to them הכי אמר ריש לקיש *hachi amar Reish Lakish* משמיה דגברא
רבא *mishmeih de-gavra rabba* this is what ריש לקיש *Reish Lakish* said
in the name of a great person ומנו רבי חנינא *umano Rebbi
Chanina* it's רבי חנינא *Rebbi Chanina* אשתו של אדם מערבת שלא מדעתו
she-lo mi-da-ato. *ishto shel adam me'arreves shelo mida'ato* a person's wife can
do it without his acquiescence and that is right and that is
even the language of מערבת *me'arreves* is not even שוכר *socher* you
know sometimes you might think that for שכירות *sekhirus* and the whole
that whole thing you know maybe we have a we make it
easier it's more of a trick okay but here it's even for
the עירוב eruv, *eiruv* itself the the wife can do it שלא
מדעתו she-lo mi-da-ato. *shelo mida'ato* without the person's knowledge okay now the
question is going to be let's say the person actually has refused
which is this case let's take a look at the next story
ההוא תורזינא *hahu turzina* דהוה בשבבותיה דרבי יהודה בר אושעיא *de-havu beshivutei
d'Rebbi Yehuda bar Oshaya* similar story you know a weapons officer head
of the armory was in the neighborhood of רבי יהודה בר אושעיא
*Rebbi Yehuda bar Oshaya* אמרו ליה *amru lei* אוגר לן רשותך *ogir
lan reshushach* rent us your property לא אוגר להו *lo ogir lehu*
he wouldn't אתו לקמיה דרבי יהודה בר אושעיא *atu lekamei d'Rebbi Yehuda
bar Oshaya* they came to רבי יהודה בר אושעיא *Rebbi Yehuda bar
Oshaya* אמרו ליה *amru lei* they said to him מהו למיגר מדביתהו
*mahu le-meigar mideveithayu* can we rent from his wife לא הוה בידיה
*lo hava beyadei* he didn't know the answer אתו לקמיה דרב מתנה
*atu lekamei de-Rav Masna* so they went to רב מתנה *Rav Masna*
לא הוה בידיה *lo hava beyadei* רב מתנה *Rav Masna* didn't know
אתו לקמיה דרבי יהודה *atu lekamei de-Rebbi Yehuda* they went to רבי
יהודה *Rebbi Yehuda* אמרו להו *amru lehu* הכי אמר שמואל *hachi amar
Shmuel* so back to רבי יהודה *Rebbi Yehuda* in the name of
שמואל *Shmuel* here's what שמואל *Shmuel* says אשתו של אדם מערבת שלא
מדעתו *ishto shel adam me'arreves shelo mida'ato* a person's wife can do
it even against his even without his knowledge or here it would
be against his will okay and that's presumably not only by שכירות
*sekhirus* but even by עירוב eruv *eiruv*. So although we just got
through שמואל *Shmuel* insisting against רב *Rav* that you need to do
have a third party to do this transference right when it's your
property and you want everybody to own it here we're now sort
of the flip case not I'm trying to get my property owned
by everybody else I'm trying to go to you and get you
to contribute your property your food okay but because it but here
we also can do like on the one hand if it's a
rental where the whole thing is a little bit of a farce
anyway remember the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says it's שכירות רעועה *sekhirus re'ua*
and so on we can get it from the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
actually if you remember before had a whole trick I don't know
if you remember where it said if the non-Jew won't rent the
property hire yourself out to the non-Jew and then you become the
working hand of the non-Jew and then you can rent out for
him so by the rental of the non-Jew we're familiar with these
tricks okay but here even if it's to actually get you to
contribute food from your house I can go you know to this
to a man's wife who technically doesn't have rights to take the
food without her husband's acquiescence and she can do it because it's
seen ultimately to be in this person's best interest okay which is
going to be a little bit not in his best interest doesn't
care yeah but he's not losing anything it's not his food okay
so then we can have more tricks okay and I suppose this
is a זכות *zechus* you're saying it's he's saying it needs to
be done in the name of everybody in the name of everybody
right so to do that when I transfer the property we still
need to go through the act of a מעשה קנין *maise kinyan*
that was debated רב *Rav* and שמואל *Shmuel* when I'm getting your
property to actually get your food so the only issue is can
I be taking it without your acquiescence you know or without your
knowledge now before we said צריך להודיע tzarich lehodiya *tsarikh lehodi'a* if
I'm actually taking your food I have to inform you here we're
saying that the wife can do it without the husband's knowledge or
maybe even against his will so let's keep on going so it
says מיתיבי *meiseve* I'm sorry so he said so this case was
מערבת *me'arreves* so we're assuming if it's true for עירוב eruv. *eiruv*
we're assuming right שכירות *sekhirus* מיתיבי *meiseve* נשים שעירבו ונשתתפו שלא מדעת
mi-da-at בעליהן *nashim she'eirvu venishtu'tefu shelo mida'at ba'aleihen* we have a ברייתא
*braisa* if women or wives part of the עירוב eruv, *eiruv* or
the שיתוף shituf, *shituf* without their husband's knowledge and they gave the
the food which is I assume it's going to happen most of
the time you're going to go door to door collecting the food
you know you're going to get a lot of times the wife
will answer the door אין עירובה עירוב eruv. ואין שיתופה שיתוף shituf?
*ein eiruvah eiruv ve'ein shitufah shituf* it's not good and As we
said at the top of the עמוד, right, you have to inform
people when you're using their food. So how does this work? Now,
the גמרא Gemara says לא קשיא, lo kashya, הא דאסר הא דלא
אסר, ha de-assar ha de-lo assar, big difference. Is your lack of
participation going to make the courtyard not usable by other people? Okay,
you could have a scenario where you might remember before where you
have let's say one courtyard and this courtyard is between a street
on this side and a street on that side. And one street
is more than common used and the other is the less common
use. So I don't participate in the less common use street, I
don't make it forbidden to you guys because I'm actually connected to
this other street. Okay, so in that case where my participation, if
I do or don't participate, won't affect whether or not the street
can be used by you guys—it'll affect whether I can use the
street but not whether it can be used by you guys—then somebody
cannot get my contribution against my will. I'm not a problem for
you, you can't demand that I contribute. But in this street here
that I'm a part of, or in the courtyard that the houses
are part of, if I don't contribute, it's a problem for everybody.
Okay, so in that type of a case, you basically can get,
you know, if you have access to my food, you don't have
to ask my permission. Okay, it is seen there that, you know,
now, so it's interesting, although I benefit in both cases, right, the
fact—we don't just base on the fact that I would benefit because
I'd be able to use it. It's the fact that without your
participating, you're getting in everybody else's way, and therefore we can sort
of make you participate. Okay, which is interesting, sort of gets almost
to בבא בתרא Bava Batra discussions about when you have people that
are part of the same city, the idea about, you know, being
sort of forced to participate in communal needs. Okay, so here it
becomes very interesting. Someone's granted a divorce because really he wants to
do it. Right, that is some of the logic is there. Right.
So here we're going to talk about—now so far we're saying that
you have let's say legitimate access to the food maybe, yeah, your
food in your house or the wife gives you the food, but
you don't have his explicit permission. What about actually bursting in and
taking the food? So let's keep on reading. What if he says
no? Or if he says no, which actually we had the case
of him saying no, which I guess your point about he says
no but we say we don't care, right, 'cause the גמרא Gemara
seems to be saying even if he says no based on the
earlier story. הקי נמי מסתברא hachi nami mistavra that also makes sense,
ואי לאו הכי קשיא דשמואל אשמואל ve-i lav hachi kashya de-Shmuel a-Shmuel
otherwise we'd have a contradiction on שמואל דאמר שמואל de-amar Shmuel 'cause
שמואל said before that his wife could give it without his knowledge,
and שמואל said elsewhere אחד מבני מבוי שרגיל להשתתף עם בני מבוי
echad mi-benei mavoi she-ragil le-hishtatef im benei mavoi that if one person
normally participates in the מבוי mavoi ולא נשתתף ve-lo nishtatef and he
did not participate, בני מבוי נכנסים לתוך ביתו ונוטלין שיתופן ממנו בעל
כרחו benei mavoi nichnasim le-toch beito ve-notlin shitufan mimeno ba-al karcho they
can go in and walk into his house and get him to
participate against his will. So the גמרא Gemara says but רגיל אין
ragil in only if he normally participates, שאין רגיל לא she-ein ragil
lo if he doesn't normally participate, no. So how—what's the story? Can
you take the שיתוף שלא מדעתו? shituf she-lo mi-da-ato? Here it seems
to make a difference whether I'm a normal participant or not normal.
Doesn't seem like you can always do it שלא מדעתו. I know,
but even בעל כרחו. ba-al karcho. I know, even בעל כרחו, ba-al
karcho, right, even which is even more than שלא מדעתו. So the
גמרא Gemara says anyway, what's the difference? לאו שמע מינה, lo shma
mina, so you see the difference is whether you make it forbidden.
Now how does that have to do with רגיל? ragil? So תוספות
Tosafos says because in this scenario I gave you that this courtyard
opens up into two streets, the street I normally participate in is
seen as the default street I'm a part of. And that's the
street that if I don't continue to participate, I make it forbidden
to everybody else. So that's why the street that I make it
problems for, they can actually force me to participate in the עירוב.
eruv The street that I don't make problems for, then I have
to be a willing participant. So it's quite fascinating, it really means
that all of the demand that it be מדעת if you're not
taking my food to be my food, you have to go through
a ritual of transferring ownership, okay, but if you're actually using my
food, then if I would my lack of participation would create problems,
you can actually forcibly get me to contribute the food. And תוספות
Tosafos says, tries to tone down the גמרא Gemara a little bit,
and he says when it says they נוטלין בעל כרחו, notlin ba-al
karcho, it means that his wife gives it. It doesn't mean that
you actually bang in the door. 'Cause the whole previous discussion had
been that, you know, at least somebody was actually giving the food
and you weren't going in and grabbing it. But again, it sounds
more radical in the גמרא Gemara itself. Okay. And then תוספות Tosafos
has a whole question, what about if the kids can do it?
You go to the door and neither the mother or the father
are home, and the kids are home, can they contribute? What exactly
is the limit to this idea of בעל כרחו, ba-al karcho, how
much literally do we really mean that? Okay. So now the גמרא
Gemara. says like this, לימא מסייע ליה leima msaye-a lei let me
try to give support, כופין אותו לעשות לחי וקורה למבוי. kofin oto
la-asot lechi ve-kora le-mavoi. You can force somebody to, you know, make
contribute presumably to the building of the לחי lechi or the קורה.
kora. So you see, this is like I said, it's almost like
בבא בתרא Bava Batra issues. You know, we need things for the
benefit of the. of the whole community, you can be forced to
participate and your sitting out is a problem for everybody else. So
here we can force you to contribute to the building of the
לחי lechi or the קורה kora to make the fourth wall for
the מבוי. mavuah. So you see it's a similar idea. So the
גמרא Gemara says: No, שאני התם דליכא מחיצה. shani hasam deleika mechitza.
There it's different that there are no walls. What does it mean?
It means that the way רש"י Rashi says it is, the lack
of walls is considered to be a more practical concern for the
people of the מבוי; mavuah; it's not just the halachic issue. I
gotta tell you, this לחי lechi or קורה kora is just an
invisible wall, but anyway, but תוספות Tosafos says there it's maybe something
like more of a physical construction for the courtyard, maybe it's more
obvious you can be forced to participate. That is more like בבא
בתרא. Bava Basra. A halachic type of a participation, maybe less so.
תוספות Tosafos says a different גרסא. girsa. He says תוספות Tosafos says
the actual original גרסא, girsa, he says רש"י Rashi changed it. The
actual original גרסא: girsa: שאני התם דאיכא מחיצות, shani hasam de'ika mechitzos,
not דליכא מחיצות. deleika mechitzos. And what it means is that, let
me see what תוספות Tosafos says, oh, תוספות says there once you
actually build a wall I don't care whether you force my participation
or not, the physical reality of a wall is halachically significant. Right?
If I've got four walls here I don't say oh well, was
somebody forced to contribute against their will? Who the heck cares? That
doesn't affect the halachic legitimacy of the wall. Whereas by the עירוב,
eiruv if the whole idea of the עירוב eiruv is that we're
equal partners in this courtyard conceptually it's about us all willingly participating.
So there you might not be able to force my participation. There
it's not just a physical reality you're trying to create, you're trying
to create a sense of partnership and it might require my genuine
participation. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara does not know how much I
can actually be forced to participate in an עירוב. eiruv Now the
גמרא says now there's these three words: לשון אחר מצד שני, lashon
acher mitzad sheni, which means nothing. And if you look at the
side it's quite fascinating. If you look at the side comment it
says here: שלש תיבות הללו משוללי הבנה למאד. shalosh teivos hallalu meshulalei
havana lim'od. These three words, I don't know, in my, in the
גמרא I was looking at yesterday it was on the right hand
margin, here it's on the left hand margin, it's tiny little print.
It says these three words are completely incomprehensible. ועיין בתיקוני כלי שרת
ועיין במר פנים ובשעת דפוס ויניציאה משנת שפח ובדפוס שלוניקי משנת שח
ליתנהו. v'ayein b'sikunei klei shareis v'ayein b'mar panim uv'shas defus venetzia mishnas
shin-pei-ches uv'defus saloniki mishnas shin-ches leisneihu. In certain various editions of the
גמרא these three words aren't there. Okay, so these are three bizarre
words here in the גמרא. איתמר, so we're going to skip them.
איתמר, רבי חייא בר אשי אמר: עושין לחי אשירה. Itmar, Rabbi Chiya
bar Ashi amar: osin lechi asheira. You can make a לחי lechi
out of an אשירה. asheira. We're back to the אשירה. asheira. Okay?
So it's אסור בהנאה, assur b'hana'ah, but presumably it's interesting, getting the
ability to halachically carry in the מבוי mavuah is not considered direct
הנאה; hana'ah; you're not getting physical benefit from it. It's quite interesting.
And halachically it can work as the לחי, lechi, as the post.
וריש לקיש אמר: עושין קורה אשירה. V'Reish Lakish amar: osin kora asheira.
You can even make the קורה, kora, the beam, out of the
אשירה. asheira. מאן דאמר קורה כל שכן לחי. Man de'amar kora kol
shekein lechi. If you can do the beam, certainly the post. ומאן
דאמר לחי, אבל קורה לא. U'man de'amar lechi, aval kora lo. Why?
כתותי מיכתת שיעוריה. Kisusei michsas shiureih. Because this is an idea we
sometimes say by עבודה זרה, since there's a מצוה mitzvah to destroy
it, it's like it's already destroyed. It's like the שיעור shiur is
burnt up. And therefore the קורה kora has to be able to
support a brick. Whereas a לחי lechi does not have any minimum
width. So תוספות says, but at least it has a minimum height.
It might not have a minimum width, but it has a minimum
height. So okay, תוספות doesn't know exactly why there's a difference. He
says, I mean, he has a couple of reasons. But anyway, that's
at least the difference that by a קורה kora we have more
of a demand of a certain width and therefore making it out
of an אשירה asheira is not good. It's also not addressing the
issues about the איסור הנאה. issur hana'ah. All right, let's get on
a little bit. No, מהו דעבדינן עד השתא? Mahu de'avdinan ad hashta?
What did we do so far? The משנה Mishna says that you
have to transfer ownership if you want to use your food and
this is what the rabbi has to do or whoever's doing it
for everybody under the עירוב, eiruv, transfer the ownership of it to
everybody and you need a third party or second party, whatever, to
be the receiving party for everybody else. And it has to be
independent of your own control, so it cannot be your children, or
it could be other people's children, it can't be your kids or
it can't be your slave. But you transfer it and then everybody
takes possession of it. רב said that that's not necessary; you don't
need to actually transfer, against the משנה. Mishna. In the end we
rule that you do have to transfer, whether it's for this, whether
it's for שיתוף, עירוב תחומין, eruv techumin, עירוב חצירות, eruv chatzeiros, even
עירוב תבשילין eruv tavshilin if you want it to work you actually
have to transfer. When it comes though to people actually contributing their
food, how much do they have to do it with awareness and
willingly or so on? There we started saying, no, no, if you're
getting in the way then we can sort of maybe force you
to contribute. So the wife can contribute the husband's property without his
awareness; maybe we can even break into... And take the food and
so on and therefore if we're using your food there's a lot
less of a need for you to be aware because you're actually
getting in people's way. Okay so now we get on to the
next משנה. mishnah. נצמית האוכל. nismait ha'ochel. Now let's say we're it's
funny we're going in reverse order and in a minute we're about
to say what the minimum amount of food is but let's say
the food became decreased like from the minimum you gathered the food
before שבת and then ושיתוף מבואות v'shituf mevo'ot and then you know
on Friday whatever you gathered it last week and then this week
Friday there was less than the minimum amount some of it got
eaten by rats or something who knows. מוסיף ומזכה mosif u'mezakeh you
can go ahead and add to it. אין צריך להודיע ein tzarich
lehodiya you don't have to inform them especially because you're adding your
food to it so again you don't have to let them know.
נתוספו עליהן nitosefu aleihen now let's say new people joined the street
and the neighborhood since last שבת and therefore you need more food
for them so מוסיף ומזכה mosif u'mezakeh so the way רש"י Rashi
reads this is if you're going to add the food from your
own so you do it without their awareness
you're just מזכה mezakeh to
them of your own food. If you however get their food to
now because they're now new dwellers of the neighborhood and you're going
to use their food then צריך להודיע tzarich lehodiya you would have
to inform them. So basically the rule is as before your food
you need the second party to transfer the ownership to. Their food
they have to be aware although as the גמרא just said that's
only if they're not getting in the way if they're getting in
the way you don't have to make them aware. Now כמה הוא
שיעורן kama hu shiuran what is the minimum amount of food that
you need? בזמן שהן מרובין bizman she'hen merubin if there's a lot
of them so people in the מבוי mavoi מזון שתי סעודות לכולן
mazon shtei seudot lekulam and this is why I've always been saying
a box of מצות matzos actually it's not so much you two
meals worth for everybody could be a million people in the city
two meals worth for everybody is enough. Okay now בזמן שהן מועטין
bizman she'hen muatin if there's a very small number כגרוגרת לכל אחד
ואחד kegrogeret lechol echad v'echad each one has to contribute the size
of a pressed fig a pressed fig. Okay. אמר רבי יוסי amar
Rabbi Yossi במה דברים אמורים bameh devarim amurim בתחלת עירוב bitechilat eruv
when is it true that you have these minimums when you initially
make the עירוב. Notice how we smoothly moved from תחומין tchumin from
שיתוף מבואות shituf mevo'ot to עירוב חצרות. eruv chatzerot. אבל בשיורי עירוב
aval bishiyurei eruv when you actually did it and now you have
a little food left you don't have all that you started with
כל שהוא kol shehu even the smallest amount is okay again against
the beginning of the משנה mishnah even crumbs you don't have to
reestablish the minimum. ולא v'lo why? Because לא אמרו לערב בחצרות אלא
כדי שלא תשכח את התינוקות lo amru l'arev bachatzerot ela kedei shelo
tishkach et hatinokot because he's assuming that you're already doing your שיתוף
מבואות shituf mevo'ot so why are we doing an עירוב together with
a שיתוף? It's only so the kids don't forget and therefore we're
going to be lenient and if you even have a tiny bit
left at the end it'll be okay. Now we actually פסקן pasken
as I told you that if you use bread for the שיתוף
מבואות shituf mevo'ot you don't have to do an עירוב חצרות eruv
chatzerot which is why it makes it so much simpler. The rabbi
takes one box of מצות matzos two meals worth bread for everybody
in the whole city ten thousand people וגמרנו. v'gamarnu. Alright I guess
could we go two more minutes get a little bit further let's
get to do that. Okay so במאי עסקינן bemai askinan what are
we talking about? אילימא במין אחד ilima bemin echad if it's that
after you gathered up I don't know wine and now you want
to replace it with oil so מאי איריא נצמית mai irya nismait
אפילו כלה afilu kala I'm sorry no the same it was wine
and you want to add back wine and again this is assuming
that you want to basically take from their food without necessarily informing
them. Okay so מאי איריא נצמית אפילו כלה נמי mai irya nismait
afilu kala nami then even if it completely finishes as long as
you're taking more of the same presumably since you got their okay
initially with wine you can go and take more of their wine
to make up the difference.
אלא בשני מינין ela bishnei minin it must be that now you
want
to take oil and you want to take their oil and therefore
it's a problem because and therefore it's if it okay well let's
see it's oil so אפילו נצמית נמי לא afilu nismait nami lo
if that's true then even if it's
meaning if you wanted to take wine more
wine then even
if all the wine had been used up you could go do
it presumably the משנה mishnah says that there's less than you started
with but it's not all used up but I don't understand if
you wanted to take something new like oil you can't do that
without making them aware even if you have some of the wine
left over. אפילו afilu so דתניא detanya we תנא tanna'd a בריתא
braita כלה האוכל kala ha'ochel if the food was completely destroyed you
know no longer around ממין אחד mimin echad if you want to
replace the original thing like it was wine and you want to
take wine אין צריך להודיע ein tzarich lehodiya you can take their
food and you don't have to inform them. משני מינין mishnei minin
from two different types of if you want now replace it with
oil צריך להודיע you have to inform them so basically our this
בריתא braita talks about it being fully used up and distinguishes between
one מין min and two and none of that was understood. in
the משנה. Mishna. So the גמרא says, where were we? איבעית אימא
מין אחד, i ba'is eima min echad, איבעית אימא שתי מינין. i
ba'is eima shtei minin. I can answer either way. איבעית אימא מין
אחד, i ba'is eima min echad, it's if you want to replace
it with wine, and מאי נסמט נסמט, mai nismat nismat, meaning when
the משנה Mishna says there's less, it really means it was completely
used up. So don't overread the case of the משנה Mishna where
it says less. The משנה Mishna says that it means if the
עירוב was completely used up, you can go ahead and retake the
food of the עירוב even without informing them as long as you're
taking the same stuff. So originally everybody contributed wine, you have access
to everybody's wine cellar, the original עירוב was used up, you want
to take more wine, go ahead, you can do it, you don't
have to inform them, they've already agreed to participate with wine. And
איבעית אימא שתי מינין, i ba'is eima shtei minin, or we're talking
about it's two things, that you want now use oil, and כלו
שאני. kalu shani. When it's completely used up, maybe that's different, maybe
they get to have another voice about, you know, another opinion. But
if you wanted to take if you needed a little extra food
and you didn't need to start all over again, then you could
even take from a different type of a thing, from the oil,
even without informing them. So the basic upshot of this is, everybody
contributed to the עירוב, we now need to replenish the supplies. So
since you've already agreed to contribute, okay, assuming we need your agreement,
although a minute ago we said, you know, we said that if
you really get in the way we really don't even need your
agreement, but in a scenario where we do need your agreement, okay,
since you've already agreed and I need to replenish, I can replenish
without asking you. If I have access to your stuff, I can
replenish without asking you. However, in certain circumstances, like I need to
do it all over again from the beginning, there's no wine left,
and I want to do it with something else, I want to
now use oil, in that's a circumstance I have to get your
buy-in as well. But anytime I'm sort of just restoring the situation,
it's a continuation of the past and I don't need your buy-in
again. Okay, I guess we will continue here tomorrow, we have to
find a way to catch up. But then can't I just take
my own and forget you? What? Yeah, you can always take your
own and forget me.